בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody.
Today's דף daf is מ"ח, mem chet, 48, the penultimate דף daf
of the פרק. perek. Tomorrow we will, God willing,
finish, not the פרק, perek, the מסכת. masechet. We pick up today
on מ"ז עמוד ב', mem zayin amud bet, איתמר itmar by the
asterisk, about ten lines from the bottom, last word on the line,
איתמר. itmar. Okay,
and we were having this issue right in the משנה mishnah about
the workers and the storekeeper, and storekeeper says he gave the workers
their food, the workers say they didn't receive it, and the חכמים
chachamim say they both take an oath to בעל הבית. ba'al habayis.
בעל הבית ba'al habayis pays out twice even though one of them
is definitely making a false oath. You know, you can't decide which
one, so neither one has to give up their rights. ובין ננס
U'Ben Nanas basically says that they both get paid even without an
oath, at least that's one version of the משנה. mishnah. There's a
slightly different text. Anyway, and רבי Rebbi says that also seems to
sort of side with בן ננס, Ben Nanas, and the way the
גמרא Gemara explained the position of רבי Rebbi was,
well, there were two versions. Either that according to one version, he
basically still held that they both take an oath, but according to
the other version, no, the worker swore to the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis and the בעל הבית ba'al habayis in the presence of the
storekeeper and the בעל הבית ba'al habayis paid the workers but the
בעל הבית ba'al habayis did not pay the storekeeper. So we basically
have three options: they both take an oath and they both get
paid; no one takes an oath and they both get paid; or
one version the גמרא Gemara had according to one interpretation of רבי
Rebbi was that the workers get paid with an oath, the storekeeper
does not get paid. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. איתמר, Itmar, was taught, שתי כיתי עדים המכחישות זו את זו.
shtei kitoi edim hamachishot zo et zo. So you have two groups
of עדים, edim, ראובן ושמעון Reuven and Shimon and then לוי ויהודה,
Levi and Yehudah, and they're saying contradictory testimonies. One says ראובן, Reuven,
you know, we were at, you know, at this place at this
time and ראובן Reuven borrowed a hundred dollars from שמעון, Shimon, and
the other people say no, we were exactly at that point at
that time and ראובן Reuven did not borrow a hundred dollars from
שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so they're not עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, they're not
saying you were with us somewhere else, they're saying contradictory testimonies. So
one is telling the truth, one is lying, we don't know which
is which. So אמר רב הונא זו באה בפני עצמה מעידה וזו
באה בפני עצמה מעידה. Amar Rav Huna, zo ba bifnei atzmah me'idah
vezo ba bifnei atzmah me'idah. So you know one of them is
lying but you don't know which one, so each one retains its
חזקת כשרות, chasakas kashrus, its presumption of being honest and kosher witnesses,
and you, they, and therefore when in a different court case each
group of עדים edim can still be valid עדים. edim. You know,
you will always presume that it was the other group. So on
Monday you hear ראובן ושמעון Reuven and Shimon for court case A,
and Tuesday you hear לוי ויהודה Levi and Yehudah for court case
B, and you פסקן pasken both A and B based on, you
know, their respective testimony, and you just handle each case separately even
though you know stepping back that one of them is invalid, but
since you can't pick up which one, you handle, you know, they're
allowed to come to separate court cases and everything is fine. The
one thing you can't do is you can't have ראובן Reuven and
לוי Levi join together in a court case because then you know
that they will both, one of those, you know, is, if you
have two groups of witnesses, why don't I ever
have, there we go, the whole coming
off this whiteboard, who puts this tape? What? חנן Hanan brought you
a beautiful eraser.
I know, I know. Alright, it's gone.
I don't know, I don't know.
No, I think it's on my desk, I don't know where I
put it. Okay, anyway, it's fine. Okay, anyway, this is group one
and, oh I need another marker though,
and this is group two. Do not take the colors to mean,
you know, honest. Okay,
so each one can come in their separate court cases even though
one is פסול pasul because you don't know which is פסול, pasul,
so each one retains its presumption of being kosher. But what you
can't have is you can't let them combine the two, let's say
two parts of a court case, the same court case, or you
can't have a group made up of one of these because then
you know one of that group of עדים edim is פסול. pasul.
But if they come as separate groups to different courts, each one
will retain its presumption of being kosher. זו באה בפני עצמה מעידה
וזו באה בפני עצמה מעידה. Zo ba bifnei atzmah me'idah vezo ba
bifnei atzmah me'idah. רב חסדא אמר בהדי סהדי שקרי למה לי. Rav
Chisda amar bahadi sahadi shikri lama li.
What do I have to deal with at these, you know, lying
witnesses? One group is invalid and since I don't know which I
refuse to accept in the future either group. Okay, so that's the
debate. Now we're going to apply this scenario to, we're going to
sort of figure out the implications of this debate in a couple
of related scenarios. שני מלוים ושני לוים ושני שטרות. Shnei malvim ushnei
lovim ushnei shetarot. Okay,
so if you have, let
me get a third color, this dry erase.
Okay, if you have
a
case where,
okay, you have
he lent money to him, right, that's case one and that's case
two, so you have two lenders, two borrowers, each one has a
שטר, shtar, okay, and in this guy's שטר shtar are signed ראובן
Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, and in this guy's שטר shtar is signed
לוי Levi and יהודה, Yehuda, okay, so that's one scenario, okay, so
that case, each case comes separately to court, presumably they come the
same day, they're separate court cases, and you'll trust these witnesses and
have this and have him pay, and then these witnesses and have
him pay, okay, so it's like two separate court cases, okay, fine.
So according to the opinion that says that they remain כשר, kosher,
according to the opinion that says that they remain invalid, you don't
accept any of the witnesses ever, okay, so that points out,
these are coming after
they contradicted each other, yeah. Okay, so, שני מלוין ושני לווין ושני
שטרות, shnei malvin u'shnei lovin u'shnei shtarot, היינו פלוגתא, hainu plugta,
that's the debate, according to the position of רב הונא, Rav Huna,
each שטר shtar is כשר kosher and according to the position of
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, each, you know, you whatever, you never accept
these witnesses.
Now, מלוה ולוה ושני שטרות, malveh v'loveh u'shnei shtarot, יד בעל השטר
על התחתונה, yad ba'al hashtar al hatachtonah, now let's say you've got
one guy, okay, he's the one borrower, one lender, excuse me, and
he's coming with two documents, alright, so in this case רב הונא
Rav Huna basically says, even רב הונא Rav Huna who says I
take each one separately, like רב הונא Rav Huna says now, if
this guy were smart, okay, what he probably would do would be
come one day with this שטר shtar and the next day with
the next שטר shtar and just bring each one separately, let each
case be adjudicated by itself, okay, but it seems like we're talking,
you know, and I don't know if we would say retrospectively reassess,
presumably each case is a separate case, but what we're talking somehow
about is that somehow he's putting them together, so it seems. So
then we're saying like he can't award you both שטרות shtarot because
one of those is invalid, alright. Now, again, if he were smart
at that case, what he would do is he would drop the
lower value שטר shtar and produce the higher value שטר, shtar, okay,
but he didn't do that. He produced both שטרות. shtarot. So if
he produces both שטרות shtarot at the same time, so then what
it's basically saying is we have two testimonies here. Let's say this
שטר shtar let's say is worth a hundred dollars
and this is worth two hundred. So what we basically as the
בית דין, beit din, since he was stupid and he came all
the same time and he produced them both at the same time,
okay, so what we basically are saying is is that we have,
we're looking at both sets of testimony and we're saying one of
them is false, one says 100, one says 200, I mean, the
testimony might not be false, but it's being testified by false witnesses,
right, once one of them the lying one here becomes a false
witness from that point on. It's not just that we suspect they're
lying, it's sort of like they're a false witness but we don't
know who it is. So one of these testimonies is based on
false witness. We don't know which one it is. So what we
have to do is we can only take the, you know, what
do you call it, we can only take the minimum, the one
that is like, you know, the minimum testimony because at least that
one is true according to both of them, so we take the
hundred dollars. Now the problem, wait a minute, is it one לוה?
loveh? It's one לוה, loveh, wait a minute. שני מלוין ושני לווין
ושני שטרות, shnei malvin u'shnei lovin u'shnei shtarot,
היינו פלוגתא. hainu plugta. מלוה ולוה
ושני שטרות. malveh v'loveh u'shnei shtarot. Excuse me, yeah, that was wrong,
because then if it were separate person, it's not a minimum, they're
saying different things, okay, it's same thing,
okay, same borrower, same lender, two separate שטרות. shtarot. Now again, if
he's smart, he would just, you know, either come on separate days,
if assuming that would work, at least drop his lower שטר, shtar,
but he didn't, he produced them both at the same time. So
we say, well, minimally we have a testimony that this guy owes
you a hundred dollars. We don't know if we have a testimony
he owes you two hundred, but even if this is the correct
one, it's also testifying he owes you a hundred. So since minimally
we have a testimony he owes you a hundred, he has to
pay a hundred, the rest we don't know. Now the funny thing
would be, right, let's say this one would have
earlier liens and this one would have later liens, you know, you
might have to sort of split it, we minimally have a hundred
dollars but we also have to go by the later liens, like
we sort of take, you know, the overlap of the two testimony,
okay, when he produces them both at the same time. Yes.
Isn't this a little different? I mean in the case where two
witnesses, one says one, one says the other, isn't it possible that
one group is not necessarily
lying, but
mistaken, where in שטר shtar it's just like contradicts on its face,
I mean it's...
Yeah, I mean again, you have to presume that in this case
we're assuming whatever, that we can't assume contradiction, we have to... Yeah,
I mean again, you have to presume that in this case we're
assuming for whatever that we can't assume contradiction. We have to assume
one of them is false. But yeah, I mean that's a good
question. We'll get something similar to that in a bit. Okay? Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: יצאו שתי תחתונות. Yatzu
shetei tachtonot. יד בשלוש תחתונות, Yad bashalosh tachtonot, so you have to
take the lesser of the two. שני מלווין ולווה אחד. Shenei malvin
veloveh echad. Now, let's say, however, if one borrower, okay, but
right, one borrower but two separate, wait, is it wait, which one
is it now? שני לווין ומלווה אחד? Shenei lovin umalveh echad? I
don't want to get it wrong again. שני מלווין ולווה אחד, Shenei
malvin veloveh echad, right? Two lenders, okay, two lenders, but one borrower.
Okay, so can each one come separate to court? Right? He comes
on his day, he comes on his day, and that would be
like a separate court case. If this guy is paying out twice
and the borrower would say, wait, I'm paying out now to, you
know, yesterday I paid out to the other guy, today I'm paying
out to you, but one of those sets of witnesses was false
witnesses! Or do we say like tough luck, each one came on
a separate day and according to רב הונא, Rav Huna, as long
as the witnesses come separate they remain valid? So what's the story?
Okay?
So, שני מלווה ולווה אחד ושני שטרות היינו מתניתין. Shenei malveh veloveh
echad ushnei shtarot haynu matsnisin. That's the way that the משנה Mishnah
about can the storekeeper take an oath and the workers take an
oath and the owner pay twice? Because can the owner say, hey,
one of those oaths was false! I'm not going to pay twice.
Or do we say no, each guy had a separate court case
and you're not you don't have a right to make us force
us to look at it together. Like they had a legitimate claim
against you and they had a legitimate claim against you. So here
too, very nice that you're screaming one of those witnesses is false,
but each one comes with a separate kosher שטר. shtar. That's like
the storekeeper and the workers coming with a separate demand. So בן
ננס, Ben Nanas, who didn't like them taking a false oath in
the משנה, Mishnah, בן ננס Ben Nanas might do something here to
put an end to this case as well. Again, assuming that somehow
we became aware of it at the same time, you know? You
could imagine this happens on one year and this happens on another
year and like we're not going to combine the cases. You know
at least in the case of the משנה, Mishnah, it was all
part of the same dispute, right? And they were all sort of
all three of them were coming. Alright, but anyway, even in a
scenario where all three come, according to the חכמים Chachamim he would
pay twice, the same way they take separate oaths if they were
the storekeeper. And according to בן ננס, Ben Nanas, he might not
allow that to go through.
Okay, היינו מתניתין. Haynu matsnisin. בי לווין ומלווה אחד ושני שטרות מאי
תיקו. Bei lovin umalveh echad ushnei shtarot mai teiku. Let's say, however,
it is, okay, this guy with his two שטרות, shtarot, okay, doesn't
really matter the value right now, okay, and this is what I
was drawing before, was jumping ahead, okay, and it's this case, right?
This שטר shtar for this guy, שטר shtar for that guy. Okay,
and again, it's not clear to me if he's coming to בית
דין Beis Din and producing both שטרות shtarot at once, okay, but
let's say he is. So do we say, okay, you have two
claims against two different people, even though you're handing both שטרות shtarot
to בית דין Beis Din and say please process these two claims
for me, we're going to treat these as two separate court cases
and therefore let each שטר shtar be valid? Or are we going
to say, you know, in the end of the day, maybe look,
this is maybe even like worse than the other case because in
the other case, you know, you know at least here you're collecting,
you know, the money is being pooled at the end, right? You
know, so in the end you're collecting money and one of those
testimonies, right, was not legitimate. So maybe even if you came one
after the other. Yesterday you collected based on this שטר, shtar, how
are we today going to let you collect based on the other
שטר? shtar? One of those שטרות shtarot was invalid. Or do we
say no, each day is a separate day, each court case is
a separate case, and I'm allowed to collect one day with one
שטר shtar and one day with the other שטר. shtar. So the
גמרא Gemara does not have a resolution. תיקו. Teiku. Would that be
a case that רב הונא Rav Huna would allow to go through
or not? Okay, so that was very interesting. מתיב רב הונא בר
יהודה. Masiv Rav Huna bar Yehuda. So רב הונא בר יהודה Rav
Huna bar Yehuda asks, okay, you know,
so, אחד אומר גבוה ב מרדאות ואחד אומר שלוש עדותן קיימת. Echad
omer govah beis marda'ot ve'echad omer shalosh eidusan kayames. This is similar
to the question that חנן Chanan said about question about like maybe
sometimes we say they're mistaken and not lying.
אחד אומר גבוה ב מרדאות ואחד אומר שלוש עדותן קיימת. Echad omer
govah beis marda'ot ve'echad omer shalosh eidusan kayames. If you have people
that two people that are testifying about whether they saw the new
moon,
and one said it was like two, you know, saddles or whatever
a מרדאה marda'ah is, like you know two units high off of
the horizon as I saw the new moon, and the other said
no I saw it three units off of the horizon, higher than
the horizon, so then we say they combine because we say that
they what do you call it they that you know they're off
a little bit but they're not lying and they're actually testifying to
the same thing. אחד אומר ג ואחד אומר ה, Echad omer gimmel
ve'echad omer chamesh, if one says three and the other says five,
that's too big of a discrepancy and עדותן בטילה, eidusan betelah, you
don't combine them. ומצטרפין לעדות אחרת. Umistarfim le'eidus acheres. But you can
it sounds like each witness remains kosher and they can be used
for another testimony. Okay, so why can they be used for another
testimony? That works for רב הונא. Rav Huna. But for רב חסדא
Rav Chisda that said הני סהדי שקרי למה לי Hani sahaday shikray
lamay leh that if they're lying in one case, you know, they
can't be used in another, why does it say that these witnesses
can can go? can testify in a different case. Okay, and this
again, is the presumption here Chanan is that one of them is
actually lying. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו לעדות ממון mai
lav l'eidus mamon doesn't that mean that in some other case, you
know, if Reuven said it was at three units and Shimon said
it was at five, in some other case, Reuven can be part
of some other testimony and Shimon can be part of some other
testimony like in a court case about like somebody owing money. So
that shows against רב חסדא Rav Chisda that they remain like רב
הונא, Rav Huna, that they remain כשר. kosher. So אמר רבא, amar
Rava, no. הוא ואחר מצטרפים לעדות אחרת דראש חודש. hu v'acher mitztarfim
l'eidus acheres de-Rosh Chodesh. No, no, no. It doesn't mean another case
of like a monetary case. What it means is, is that if
Reuven said three and Shimon said five, and then along comes Levi
and Levi also says three, so then the side of three wins
out. So when it says they combine for another testimony, it doesn't
mean other than this case of testifying on the new moon they
can go ahead and testify in other court cases. No, רב חסדא
Rav Chisda would say once one of them was lying, these two
can never testify in other court cases again, unless maybe they do
תשובה, teshuva, I don't know how you do תשובה teshuva if you
say you weren't lying. But
anyway, what it means is, is that if in this case itself,
although it says a different testimony, it doesn't really mean a different
case, it means
like within this dispute that we're having I get somebody else to
back me up, and one of the sides gets another witness to
back him up, then that side will win out and the other
one will be negated.
דהוה ליה תרי de-hava lei trei כנגד חד, ke-negad chad, two against
one, ואין דבר שבמקום שנים. v'ein d'var she-be-achar b'makom shnayim. Okay,
and therefore one doesn't stand up against two and the side that
has the other witness joining him will be legitimate. Alright, so that
was interesting. That was a very nice interesting illustration here about this
case of two debating witnesses, but it was brought in because it
was similar to the case about the storekeeper and the workers
where can you allow the owner to pay both sides out even
though one of them is taking a false oath? But each one
will say, it ain't me who's taking the false oath and I
have a right to make a claim. Yeah.
I always had the impression that the ones who spoke to someone
to testify about the new moon, that the court actually really knew
the position of the moon and they just needed them to verify.
Right. Right. They would know who was telling the truth.
Yeah, that's an interesting question about like, yeah, it's an interesting question.
I mean, that comes up a lot in those משניות Mishnayot and
how much they use their own astronomical knowledge to interfere with the
process of accepting the witnesses. So it's a discussion to have when
we learn ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right?
Alright. אמר לך וניתימי בדין פירות. amar lach v'nitemei b'din peiros. Now,
let's say, now we get to the next part of the משנה,
Mishna, which is, so the classic שבועה shvua of the חנוני chenvani
was about this case of the workers. But let's say there's a
question where I basically say that the storekeeper says that I have
the box of apples, the whatever, the crate of oranges, and the
storekeeper says give me my money and I says what are you
talking about, I already paid. So that type of a case basically
he's like, I'm a כופר הכל. kofer hakol. I say I paid,
he says you owe me the money. And normally we would say
I walk away but this is a case where it's a, it
is a new type of a שבועה shvua but not a שבועה
shvua of collect, a שבועה shvua of swearing and being exempt. It's
a כופר הכל kofer hakol type of a case. Okay, that's what
the משנה Mishna says. Okay, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagreed and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said if I already have the fruit, if
I already have the box of, the crate of oranges, then I
don't even have to take a שבועה. shvua. Nobody hands over the
produce until I've actually paid the money. תניא, Tanya, אמר רבי יהודה,
amar Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says אימתי, ematai, when is
it that I would have to take a שבועה shvua that I
paid the money? בזמן שהפירות
צבורים ומונחים ושניהם עוררים עליהם, bizman she-ha-peiros tzuburim u'munachim v'shneihem orrim aleihem,
they're right there on the conveyor belt, they're at the checkout counter
and we're debating whether I paid or not. אבל הפשילן בקופתו לאחוריו
המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. aval hifshilan b'kupato l'achorav hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya.
But if I've actually put them in my sack, okay, I've taken
them
out of the shopping cart and they're in the bags and I'm
walking out of the store, right, then it's like no, then you're
not believed to say that I haven't paid you and I don't
even have to take an oath. Alright, so that's Rabbi Akiva. Now,
similarly רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. אמר לשולחני תני, amar l'shulchani teini, similarly
if there's a debate
if I gave the money changer a 20 and asked him to
give me singles, and I had the singles, and he said I
hadn't paid him the 20. So the חכמים Chachamim say I have
to take an oath that I paid already, המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה
hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya but here I have to take an oath,
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, if you already have the
change, you don't have to take an oath, of course you're believed.
וצריכא. ve-tzricha. Now you need both cases. דאי אשמעינן הך קמייתא, di
ashmian hachamaisa, if we had said the case of the produce, ובהא
קאמרי רבנן משום דפירי אבידי דמרקבי, v'hacha ka-amrei rabanan mishum d'pirei avidi
d'mirkavi, and
in that case the Rabbis say
because fruit normally rot. וכיון דמרקבי, v'kivan d'mirkavi, and since they often
will rot, לא משהו ליה. lo mashhu lei. That's why they might
disagree with רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. I understand. That's why they might
agree with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because they would say disagree because
they would say, look, normally maybe you're right that you don't let
the guy take the stuff before he's paid the money. But here,
because something the fruit could rot, maybe he lets you take the
fruit out sooner. Now, of course that's like rotten like Michael says
really, like it's just a minute so the way רש״י Rashi says
it, it's not just the fruit is going to rot, it's also
like... like I don't want you finding some little bruise on the
peach and then wanting to go and return it. Since bad stuff
can happen, I just want to pack you up with your produce
and get you, you know, get it off of the counter as
quick as possible, so that you don't start asking for exchanges. So
that's why the maybe that, you know, you were able to put
it in your bag before you paid. Okay, אבל מעות לא מירכבי
aval ma'ot lo mirkevi but money that doesn't sort of, you know,
rot, אימא מודו ליה לרבי יהודה eima modu lei le-Rabbi Yehuda maybe
they would agree to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that if I've got
the singles, I must have definitely paid the money and I don't
have to take an oath. ואי איתמר בהא ve-i itmar be-ha now
if we had just said that debate, בהא קאמר רבי יהודה be-ha
ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda maybe it's just by the money that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says I don't take an oath, אבל בהא אימא מודה
להו לרבנן aval be-ha eima modeh lehu le-Rabbanan but maybe by the
fruit he would agree that you do have to take an oath.
צריכא tzricha you have to tell me that whether it's a case
which more inclines towards the rabbis or more inclined towards רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, they disagree on both cases.
So wait, why in fruit would you, why the other way?
Same point. Same point. It's just that where whether the חידוש chiddush
is for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or for the רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay,
כשם שאמרו הפוגמת כתובתה וכן יתומים לא
יפרעו. keshem she-amru ha-pogemet ketuvatah ve-chen yetomim lo yipare'u.
Okay, so now the משנה mishna goes on to a whole list
of cases of where also there's a דרבנן שבועה, de-rabbanan shvua, a
woman who is collecting her כתובה ketuva who admits a part of
it's been paid, etc. etc. Anyway, and the last case about it
is when the orphans come to collect, they, that's the חידוש chiddush
of the משנה mishna that even when orphans are the creditors, they
have to take an oath that the father, they didn't find any
documentation, you know, that the debt had been paid and the father
didn't tell them the debt had been paid etc. Okay, so now
we're going to actually repeat something that we actually quoted yesterday. ממאן.
miman. Now, who is,
who are they coming to collect from, these orphans? אילימא מלווה, eileima
milve, if they're coming to collect from the debtor
himself, so אבוהון שקיל בלא שבועה avuhon shakil belo shvua when their
father would come with a שטר shtar to collect from the debtor,
he wouldn't have to take an oath, right? A שבועה... shvua... you
have a שטר, shtar, you collect. That's 100% proof.
ואינהו בשבועה ve-inhu bi-shvua now the father is dead and they have
the same שטר, shtar, they'd have to take an oath? Now the
answer could be why not? When the father is taking it without
it, it's because the father is saying I know that you have
not paid me up and here's the שטר. shtar. And maybe the
heirs are saying like we assume you haven't paid up the father
and here's the שטר. shtar. So maybe yes, maybe you have to
take a שבועה. shvua. So it's not clear whether the גמרא Gemara
is saying like no, that shouldn't matter, or is the גמרא Gemara
assuming the heirs are also making a ברי bari claim. The גמרא
Gemara assumes that the heirs are saying we know for sure. Okay,
so but either way the גמרא Gemara is saying like we can't
imagine why the heirs under normal cases would have to take an
oath if the father in a similar scenario wouldn't have to. But
again the question I'm raising is are we assuming that the heirs
are making a ברי bari claim, you definitely owe us the money,
or a we presume you owe us the money. Okay, but anyway
the גמרא Gemara says that can't be that the heirs are taking
an oath in a normal case. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, so here's
how to read it.
וכן יתומים מן היתומים לא יפרעו אלא בשבועה. ve-chen yetomim min ha-yetomim
lo yipare'u ela bi-shvua. Heirs are coming to collect from heirs. So
when their father would collect from the heirs of the לוה, loveh,
let's say, let's say, let's say מרדכי Mordechai is the לוה loveh
and מרדכי Mordechai is the מלווה malveh and לוי Levi is the
לוה. loveh. Okay, you like that alliteration or whatever? So
if מרדכי Mordechai is coming to collect from לוי's Levi kids,
then because, you know, they're לוי's Levi kids, like maybe they don't
know how to defend this debt. Maybe if their father were alive
he would be able to wage some argument or defense against it.
So in a normal הלכה halacha when מרדכי Mordechai is coming to
collect from לוי's Levi kids, he has to even though he has
a שטר, shtar, he has to take an oath that the שטר
shtar hasn't been paid. That's the normal הלכה halacha when the מלווה
malveh is coming to collect from the kids of the לוה. loveh.
So now when מרדכי's Mordechai kids are coming to collect from לוי's
Levi kids, they can't take an oath, so their father... it's not
like ironic. Oh, our father, you know, the father wouldn't take an
oath, we have to take an oath? No, it actually makes sense.
The father would have to take an oath, you too have to
take an oath. Now the father's oath would be, I know this
debt hasn't been paid. Your oath is that as far as we
know this debt hasn't been paid. Exactly. Okay, so הכי
קאמר וכן יתומים מן היתומים לא יפרעו אלא בשבועה. hachi ka'amar ve-chen
yetomim min ha-yetomim lo yipare'u ela bi-shvua. So when מרדכי's Mordechai kids
are coming for לוי's Levi kids, the same way מרדכי Mordechai would
take an oath with the שטר shtar that it definitely hadn't been
paid, they take an oath that as far as they know it
hasn't been paid. רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav ve-Shmuel de-amri tarvaihu, now
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both say, and we quoted this yesterday,
לא שנו אלא שמת מלווה בחיי לוה. lo shanu ela she-met malveh
be-chayei loveh. That's only if מרדכי Mordechai died, okay, while לוי Levi
was still alive. Okay,
and that's because מרדכי Mordechai himself was never obligated to take the
שבועה shvua to לוי's Levi kids. So now מרדכי Mordechai died, מרדכי's
Mordechai kids could collect from לוי Levi without a שבועה, shvua, then
לוי Levi dies and then they make their own שבועה. shvua. Okay,
אבל
מת לוה בחיי מלוה, aval met loveh be-chayei malveh, if לוי Levi
died first, then מרדכי Mordechai was חייב chayav to make a שבועה
shvua to לוי's Levi kids that the debt definitely had not been
paid. And now... and now מרדכי Mordechai dies.
Okay, אבל מת לוה בחיי מלוה כבר נתחייב מלוה לבני לוה שבועה.
aval met loveh be-chayei malveh kevar nitchayav malveh li-vnei loveh shvua. So
מרדכי Mordechai was already חייב chayav to לוי's Levi kids that the
debt had definitely not been paid, ואין אדם מוריש שבועה לבניו, ve-ein
adam morish shvua le-vanav, and he cannot pass that on to his
children. Now, what does that mean he cannot bequeath the oath to
his kids? So one way of saying it is that since when
Levy died, the הלכה halacha was effectively that this debt cannot be
collected without an oath that it has definitely not been paid, then
when Mordechai dies, the money's already like you know what do they
say like it's tied up in not in escrow. What's the phrase
they use? Like when money, when some asset is tied up in
whatever, in court. Anyway, whatever it is. Anyway, so this is that's
usually what they say with a will. What is it? Encumbered? Whatever.
Anyway, fine. I'm trying to use fancy, use some legal term I
don't know. Anyway. So, okay. But anyway, but when so if Levy
died first, then they basically you say, the rule was with this
money could only was implicitly already ruled, right, yeah, was could only
okay, yeah, fine, let's forget that. Anyway, it was implicitly ruled that
this that this money could only be taken with an oath. And
since the heirs can't take the same oath because they don't know
for sure it hasn't been paid, they just know to the best
of their ability, since they can't take an oath, okay, therefore they
can't do what was decided as the necessary thing to win the
money, they're stuck. Okay, so that's what it would
mean אין אדם מוריש שבועה לבניו. ein adam morish shvua l'vanov. It's
not literally he can't bequeath the oath, it means they can't take
the oath that was already determined was necessary
to win the case. The other way of understanding it is slightly
different. The other way of understanding it
is that you know, before like you can bequeath, a person can
bequeath
outstanding debts owned to him, right? You know, if people owe money
to Mordechai and Mordechai dies, even though it's not cash he has
in the bank, but because it's money owed to him, it's like
that money sort of passes down, you know, to his kids. But
somehow, you know, this is a funny idea and I'm only saying
it because of what the גמרא gemara is going to say later
that suggests something like this. Somehow, if now there's an idea like
this oath has gotten in the way, it sort of it almost
pushes that money further away from the מלווה. malveh. And maybe it's
so much seen as like out of his grasp. It's not just
something that can be won immediately in court once you produce the
evidence. I don't know why an oath is different than the need
for evidence. But anyway, somehow maybe they can't even like inherit the
rights to that money because of the need for taking the oath.
But that's a little bit that's trying to be a little more
literal with the phrase אין אדם מוריש שבועה לבניו, ein adam morish
shvua l'vanov, but I think the easier explanation is just it was
already decided the money could only be won with a certain oath
and the kids can't take the oath, so they're stuck.
So then what's the point of having a שטר? shtar? You can
ask. I mean the what? Is it the שטר's shtar's really supposed
to give you some good power here and it seems...
You mean when it comes to the orphans? Yeah, because these are
normal cases that somebody dies or whatever and I understand it is
really I mean you're right.
It's a very you go out of your way to,
you know, buy a שטר. shtar. Right, I mean exactly, I totally
agree. You know, put aside all the formalism, this is a completely
not a reasonable way to run a good commercial society. I 100%
agree with you. I mean, things are up... Yeah, well exactly. So
not everybody agrees to רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Most of the
rest of today's דף daf is arguing against רב Rav and שמואל.
Shmuel. So let's take a look. Okay,
so שלחו קמיה דרבי אלעזר, shalchu k'mei d'Rabbi Elazar, or רב אלעזר.
Rav Elazar. So they sent this question to רב אלעזר. Rav Elazar.
שבועה זו מה טיבה? shvua zo mah tivah? What would you say
about the שבועה shvua when the when the לוה loveh died first
and then the מלווה? malveh? Can the מלווה's malveh's kids take a
you know, still say a different type of an oath, that we
to the best of our knowledge. So שלח להו, shalach lehu, he
sent to them, יורשין נשבעין שבועת יורשין ונוטלין. yorshin nishba'in shvuat yorshin
v'notlin. Yeah, I don't rule like רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Even
if the לוה's loveh's kids dies first, the מלווה's malveh's kids can
take a different oath than their father. Their father would have taken
an oath "I definitely, definitely haven't paid it." They'll take an oath
"as far as we know you haven't paid it," even if their
father was already obligated in the שבועה, shvua, you know, you have
to let society keep on running. Okay, so
שלחוה בימי רבי אמי. shalchuha b'yimei Rabbi Ami. So that's what they
sent in the name of רב אלעזר Rav Elazar and that's the
answer they got. Then they sent it in the name of presumably
sent to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for a checkup on this ruling
in the time of רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. ואמר, v'amar, he said,
כולי האי שלחו לה? kulei hai shalchu lah?
You keep on sending you what? You think if you keep on
asking you're going to get a different answer? So ואזלי אי אשכחנא
טעמא מי לא שלחינא להו? v'azli i ashkhachna ta'ama mi lo shalchina
lehu? If I find some other some reason, like if I find
any other information relevant to this, you know, trust me, I'll update
you if I find anything else to say. You know, maybe they
were wanted to
know like maybe they were arguing with the ruling of רב Rav
and שמואל, Shmuel, have you changed your mind? Anyway, so מי לא
שלחינא
להו. mi lo shalchina lehu. אלא אמר רב אמי, ella amar Rav
Ami, but רב אמי Rav Ami said, הא דאתי לידן נימא בה
מילתא. ha d'ati l'yadan neima bah milta. Look, since you've asked the
question, even though our position hasn't changed, I'll at least say tell
you the following slightly nuanced piece of information. Okay. עמד בדין ומת.
amad b'din u'mes. If you want to know when I, we, or
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or whatever would agree to רב Rav and
שמואל, Shmuel, it would be in the following case. Let's say Mordechai
brought Levy's kids... to an actual court case and the court basically
ruled, or maybe even ruled, whatever you know, but it was clear
it was going to rule, okay, or did rule, and it said
you can get that money when you take an oath. And then
מרדכי Mordechai died. So if the פסק Psak did was already that
you need to take the following oath, then מרדכי's Mordechai kids are
out because they can't take the oath. Okay,
עמד בדין ומת, Amad B'din Umes, then כבר נתחייב מלווה לבני לוה
שבועה, Kvar Nitchayev Malveh Livnei Loveh Shvua, then it was already actually
ruled that he had to take the oath ואין אדם מוריש שבועה
לבניו V'ein Adam Moresh Shvua L'banav and he can't pass down that
same oath to his kids, his kids would only be able to
take a different oath, and then they would be out. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ואין אדם מוריש... V'ein Adam Moresh... לא עמד
בדין ומת, Lo Amad B'din Umes, but if he
didn't actually have the court case, then we're saying like we always
said before, יורשין נשבעין שבועת יורשין ונוטלין Yorshin Nishba'in Shvuat Yorshin V'notlin
and they collect. So מתקיף לה רב נחמן: Matkif Lah Rav Nachman:
So רב נחמן Rav Nachman asked, אטו בית דינא קמחיב לשבועה? Atu
Beis Dina Kamchaiv Lishvua? What, are you saying the בית דין Beis
Din creates the obligation of the oath? No, I would sort of
think yes, you know, I mean, maybe that's the law but it
doesn't get actually like ruled and become a formal obligation until בית
דין. Beis Din. But he says no, once the rabbis say that
under these are the ways in which you collect the money, that
obligation existed from the time that לוי Levi died. So, מעידנא
דשכיב לוה נתחייב ליה מלווה לבני לוה שבועה, Meidna D'shachiv Loveh Nitchayev
Leh Malveh Livnei Loveh Shvua, even without the court ruling, from the
moment לוי Levi died, the ruling was that the הלכה Halacha was
that, you know, the מלווה Malveh could only take it with an
oath. אלא אמר רב נחמן, Ella Amar Rav Nachman, so therefore no,
you can't make it doesn't matter whether עמד בדין Amad B'din or
not עמד בדין. Amad B'din. You know, in both cases, before or
after the court case, yes, מרדכי Mordechai needed to take an oath.
We don't make some distinction here he doesn't yet need to take
an oath, after the court case he does. In both cases he
needed to take an oath. So you just have to decide, if
מרדכי Mordechai needed to take an oath and he died, are we
going to let his kids take a slightly different oath, or are
we going to say since they can't take the exact same oath
their father did they lose out? Okay, but don't try to, you
know, split the hair between before and after the court case. Okay.
So אלא אמר רב נחמן, Ella Amar Rav Nachman, so rather רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says, אי איתא לרב ושמואל איתא ואי ליתא ליתא.
I Isa L'Rav U'Shmuel Isa V'i Lessa Lessa. So you gotta love
that, almost sounds like a tautology, but not exactly. What he's saying
is if we rule like רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, we rule
like them, and if we don't, we don't. Okay, what he basically...
well, maybe if you want to rule you can. Well, that that
we're going to get to, it really means he doesn't know how
to rule, but what it really means is, don't try to make
a distinction and rule like them halfway. Okay,
either you say that the kids have to take the same oath
of their father, and then they're out even if the father died
before the court case. Or you say we let the kids take
the oath that's relevant to them, and then they can do it
even if the father died after the court case. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלמא מספקא ליה. Alma Mistapka Leh. So you're telling
me that רב נחמן Rav Nachman doesn't know whether we rule like
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel or not? Right now this this is
going to broaden it to a larger question of, you know, you
could say it's very specific to this case, but the גמרא's Gemara
going to tie it in like it did yesterday to the question
of the משנה. Mishnah. Remember the משנה Mishnah had a question where
Michael here was חייב Chayav to make a שבועת מודה במקצת Shvuat
Modeh B'miktzas but he was חשוד על השבועה. Chashud Al Hashvua. So
we say I have to make it but I'm also חשוד על
השבועה. Chashud Al Hashvua. So it boils down to the fact that
Michael can't make the שבועה Shvua that he's obligated to. So does
he have to pay, or do we say when the שבועה Shvua
can't be made it's like you just, you know, take the שבועה
Shvua off the table?
Okay. So the גמרא's Gemara going to say that this issue of
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is basically the same type of thing.
Do we say when the שבועה Shvua can't be made because the
heirs can't take the same oath that their father did,
do you basically say it's like, okay, if it can't be made
it's like off the table and they have the money and they
don't have the שבועה Shvua and they're stuck. Is that what you're
going to say or not? Okay. So let's take a look. Okay,
which is what רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel do say. So אלמא
מספקא ליה, Alma Mistapka Leh,
so it sounds like רב נחמן Rav Nachman doesn't know how he
holds. ואמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן עובדא הוה וחלקו,
V'amar Rav Yosef Bar Minyomi Amar Rav Nachman Uvda Havah V'chaklu, that
in רב נחמן Rav Nachman פוסק Paskin in this case where Michael
owes me a שבועה Shvua and neither of us can take an
oath, he פוסק Paskin like רב יוסף Rav Yosef that we split
the difference. So here too the logical thing to be would be
to say, the orphans take the שבועה Shvua that they're obligated in
and you split the difference. Okay, even though you can't make the
שבועה Shvua of the father. What happens when you can't make the
שבועה Shvua you need to make? According to רב יוסף Rav Yosef
you split it. So here too you should say split it. So
why does he say I don't know whether to go like רב
ושמואל? Rav U'Shmuel? He's considering zero or a hundred. But based on
his פסק Psak of the משנה Mishnah he should be saying fifty.
All right. לדבריו דרבי מאיר קאמר ולאו ליה סבירא
ליה. L'divreih D'Rabbi Meir Ka'amar V'la Lo Svira Leh. No, no, no.
What he is saying is like, personally, I hold like רב יוסף
Rav Yosef and I would hold in a case like this, you
know, maybe they take the שבועה Shvua of the orphans, they don't
take the שבועה Shvua of the father and you split. But according
to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who argues on רב יוסף Rav Yosef
and says remember that strange line חזרה שבועה למקומה, Chazra Shvua Limkomah,
so that I don't know. Should we say that means don't take
the שבועה Shvua and don't collect, or does it mean don't take
the שבועה, Shvua, take the שבועה Shvua that you can make, but
don't take the you can't take the שבועה Shvua of the father
and you do collect? So that's why I don't know whether to
go like רב ושמואל, Rav U'Shmuel, that's either zero or a hundred.
All right, and I don't know which way to go according to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, personally I would hold split it. hold the
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir side of the debate I wouldn't know which
way to go. Okay, מיתיבי Mative רב אושעיא, Rav Oshaya, רב אושעיא
Rav Oshaya asks. Here's going to be cases where now we're gonna
have a list of cases where it seems pretty clear that the
בני מלווה Bnei Malve can take an oath to the בני לווה
Bnei Love and collect even if the לווה Love died, right, לוי
Levi died while the מלווה Malve was still alive, that then the
and then the מלווה Malve dies his kids can still take an
oath and collect. That's we're gonna have a series of cases that
are going to be a proof against רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
and we're gonna find some way to get out of it, so
let's take a look. Okay תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in here.
I'm sorry, מיתיבי Mative רב אושעיא, Rav Oshaya, רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya
asks. מתה יורשיה משביעין את כתובתה עד עשרים וחמש שנים. Mesa Yorsheha
Mashbi’in Es Kesuvasa Ad Esrim V’chamesh Shanim. So a wife a husband
died and the widow is entitled to collect her כתובה Kesuvah from
the husband's estate. Okay, and if she doesn't want to she can
live off the husband's estate for 25 years. Now let's say she
never got around to collect the כתובה Kesuvah from the husband's estate
and then she died. So it says her heirs can bring the
כתובה Kesuvah case to the court for up to 25 years. More
than 25 years they basically forfeit their rights because it was only
up to 25 years she could live off the estate, fine. We
don't care about the 25 years.
What
was the כתובה Kesuvah 25 years?
Yeah, if she's living off the estate and not getting the lump
sum. Yeah, take a look. Anyway, so but here's what's relevant for
us. What's relevant for us is that the husband died, so when
she was to come to collect from the husband's estate, she would
have to take a שבועה, Shvua, right, that is effectively like the
לווה, Love, the one who owes the money died. She would have
to take a שבועה Shvua to the husband's kids, to the heirs
of the estate, maybe her own kids, doesn't matter. Now she died.
Okay, her so it's saying her heirs can bring the כתובה Kesuvah
to the court, but how are they bringing the כתובה Kesuvah to
the court? She would have to take an oath, so obviously her
heirs can take the שבועת היורשין Shvuas Hayorshim even though they can't
take the same שבועה Shvua that she could have taken. So it
seems a pretty explicit case that the heirs of the מלווה Malve
can take an oath to the heirs of the לווה Love even
if the לווה Love dies first. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
הכא במאי עסקינן שכשנשבעה ומתה. Hacha B’mai Askinnan Shekeshenishba’a Umesa. Ah, no,
our case would be that she had already brought the כתובה Kesuvah
to the court and she took the oath to the heirs that
she was obligated to her husband's heirs and then she died. So
the oath has already been paid, as it were, has already been
submitted. And now the only question is when are her heirs going
to actually collect the money. All right, so that's obviously a very
non פשט Pshat of that case. Okay, the simple sense is of
course yes, her heirs can take the oath. Now we're gonna have
another case.
תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in here. It'd be a very unlikely
case, right, that she would take an oath and then die. That's...
Right, right, exactly. I mean, yeah, it's very... exactly.
I mean, it could, you know, the day before they're about to
rule on it she dies, you know. Okay. תא שמע, Ta Shma,
let's hear again. נשא ראשונה ומתה. Nasa Rishona Umesa. A man married
of his first wife and then she died. נשא שניה ומתה. Nasa
Shniya Umesa. And then he married his second wife and then he
died. Okay. So and then there's a whole question about each one
is coming with different כתובה Kesuvah claims, I really don't want to
get into it, but here's the key. שניה ויורשיה קודמין ליורשי
ראשונה. Shniya V’yorsheha Kodmin L’yorshei Rishona. The second wife is now coming
to collect her כתובה Kesuvah from her husband's estate. Her rights precede
the kids of the first wife. Okay, forget the first wife. That's
not relevant. She is basically we're describing this woman who's coming to
collect, the second wife, we're just focus on the second wife, coming
to collect her כתובה Kesuvah from her dead husband's estate. So her
husband died first, she's alive, right? And then it says her heirs
also collect from the husband's estate before the first wife. Okay. How
are her heirs collecting from the husband's estate? The husband died, she
was חייבת שבועה, Chayaves Shvua, then she died, okay. So her heirs
are obviously now going to take a שבועה Shvua even though it's
not the שבועה Shvua that their mother would have taken.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי שכשנשבעה ומתה. Hacha Nami Shekeshenishba’a
Umesa. Oh, it's one of these special cases again. It's we're only
talking about her heirs if she took an oath and then died
and then her heirs can come ahead and collect. Okay, again, clearly
not פשט. Pshat. תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in here. אבל יורשיו
משביעין אותה ואת יורשיה הבאין ברשותה. Aval Yorshav Mashbi’in Osa V’es Yorsheha
Habayin Birshusa. Okay,
so this is a case where a man basically says, writes to
his wife, I do not I waive my right to ask you
to make an oath if you ever if you ever come to
collect from me, you don't you'll never have to make an oath.
Okay. So this would be like if the guy dies you won't
have to make an oath to my heirs that you know whatever
hasn't been collected, you know, it paid, etc. But it says אבל
יורשיו, Aval Yorshav, excuse me, no, excuse me, you can't make I
you'll never have to make an oath to me. So for example,
if like you admit that part of the כתובה Kesuvah has been
paid, you would normally have to make an oath, but I am
waiving the right that you need to ever make an oath to
me. But if the guy dies and now she's coming to collect
from his heirs, he only waived the need for her to make
an oath to him. He never waived the need for her to
make an oath... to the heirs, okay? So אבל יורשיו, Aval yorshav,
his heirs, משביעין אותה, mashbi'in otah, they can make her take an
oath, okay? You got it? So that's the whole point, forget, you
know. It was a case where she wouldn't have to take an
oath to him, but if he's dead, then she does have to
take the normal oath to the heirs. So we've got again this
woman collecting her כתובה, ketubah, taking an oath to the heirs, and
then it says ואת יורשיה, V'et yorsheha, and her heirs also. His
heirs could also make her heirs take an oath. So once again,
what do we have? The guy died, right, and she was obligated
an oath to his children, and now her heirs are going to
make an oath to the children and collect. So it's exactly the
same case. She was obligated an oath, she died, her children can
still make an oath, okay. וסבירא ליה כרב ושמואל. v'savira lei k'Rav
u'Shmuel. So אמר רב אמר שמואל Amar Rav amar Shmuel לצדדין קתני.
l'tzadin katani. No,
no, no, it's describing two separate cases. אותה באלמנה, Otah b'almanah,
when the case where she takes an oath, that's where he died
first and she's taking an oath to his heirs. When her heirs
are taking an oath, okay, he didn't die first, she died first,
ויורשיה בגירושה, V'yorsheha b'gerusha, right? So the case
would be, I don't want to spend too much time on this,
but the case would be like this, okay?
Here she is and here he is, right? So if he dies
first, that's number one, and here's the heirs, so then חייב שבועה.
chayav shvuah. All right, she's חייב שבועה. chayav shvuah. Then she dies,
okay, and then her heirs come to collect. So that's the question
of, oh, it sounds like they can take a שבועה shvuah even
though she was חייב שבועה, chayav shvuah, they can still take the
שבועה. shvuah. Her heirs take a שבועה shvuah from his heirs. That's
what the משנה Mishnah said. Ah, you see, they can make the
שבועה shvuah even though it's not the same their mother would have
made. So it says, no, when we're talking about her heirs, we're
not talking about he died, we're talking about that they got divorced.
Okay, they got divorced, so he's also חייב chayav an amount. And
after they got divorced, she died first. Okay, she died first. So
now she never was חייב שבועה. chayav shvuah. So now her heirs
can take the normal שבועה shvuah of שבועת היורשים shvuat hayorshim that
to the best of our knowledge. And when he dies.
She never was חייב שבועה? chayav shvuah?
If they got divorced she wants her כתובה. ketubah. Yeah, but you
don't have to use a שבועה. shvuah. The שבועה shvuah is only
when she's coming to collect from heirs. Okay, and anyway he פטר
patar her from a שבועה. shvuah. Okay, so in the case where
it says her heirs from his heirs, the גמרא Gemara is saying
is, that's a case of divorce where she died first. Because if
it was a case of being widowed where he died first, it
would still be like רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel that her heirs would
not be able to take the oath. Okay, anyway, bottom line is,
we have all these cases where it says a woman's heirs take
an oath from the husband and collect from the husband's heirs the
כתובה, ketubah, and all of it seems like a pretty darn good
proof against רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel that even if you're obligated an
oath to the heirs, your heirs can take their oath and collect.
And the גמרא Gemara gets out of it by making it special
cases. Okay.
Heirs the same as his heirs? They were married aren't they the
same children from the?
No, because it's different amounts of the, could be different amounts of
the כתובה, ketubah, could be different amounts of how much property she
brought in. It's a whole discussion when you do כתובה, ketubah, but
it's not all the same flat amount. Okay? Stepkids, a lot of
other cases. What's an oath of heirs?
The oath of heirs is to the best of our knowledge. Yeah.
מיתיבי רב נתן בר הושעיא: Meitivei Rav Natan bar Hoshaia: יפה כח
הבן מכח האב. Yafeh koach haben mikoach ha'av.
The son's power is greater than the father's, שהבן גובה בין בשבועה
בין שלא בשבועה. Shehaben goveh bein b'shvuah bein shelo b'shvuah. A son
collects, can collect with an oath and without an oath. What does
it mean? So if he has a, if he's got a שטר,
shtar, okay, and he is coming to collect from orphans, so the,
normally he would take an oath, the oath that to the best
of my knowledge it hasn't been paid. But there are times he
doesn't have to take an oath. What's the time he doesn't have
to take an oath? When the father on his deathbed says you
should know that I haven't paid, that this debt has not been
paid, right? Remember that case in the משנה? Mishnah? And that actually
exempts the guy from taking an oath to the orphans, because now
he actually has testimony, has proof that at least as far as
I know, my father testified, you know, on his deathbed that it
hadn't been paid. And then he doesn't have to take an oath
to the heirs when he's coming to collect from the heirs.
And that's not a physical שטר, shtar, right? That's just word of
mouth?
No, combined with the שטר. shtar. All these cases he has a
שטר, shtar, but because he's collecting from the heirs he would normally
have to take an oath that to the best of his knowledge
it hasn't been paid, but with the father's deathbed testimony he does
not. והאב אינו גובה אלא בשבועה, V'ha'av eino goveh ela b'shvuah, but
the father himself, if he were, if he were in court, he
could be saying it hasn't been paid and we wouldn't believe him.
We would need an oath. But when he says that on his
deathbed and the son brings that testimony, the son can collect without
an oath. Okay, fine, that just seems to be simply describing what
we saw in our משנה. Mishnah. But we're going to bring it
into the רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel debate. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's
the case? היכי דמי דמית ללוה בחיי מלוה? Heichi dami d'mit loveh
b'chayei malveh? When we're saying the father, you know, we're comparing the
way the son collects from the way the father. collects. So when
the father is collecting, he's collecting from the heirs of the לוה,
lova, the לוה lova died first. דקתני, Dikatani,
so in the same scenario as when you're dealing with the father,
it's that the לוה lova died first. So now when you're dealing
with the son, you're dealing in the same scenario where the לוה
lova died first. So even in a case where the לוה lova
died first and the father had to make a שבועה, shvuah, the
son can make a different שבועה shvuah and collect. היכי דמי? Heichi
Dami? דמית לוה בחיי מלוה? Demeys Lova B'chayai Malveh? וקתני שהבן גובה,
V'katani Shehabein Goveh, בין בשבועה בין שלא בשבועה. Bein Bishvuah Bein Shelo
Bishvuah. Okay, with an oath or without an oath. So בשבועה, Bishvuah,
with an oath, means שבועת יורשין, Shvuas Yorshin, the oath of the
heirs to the best of our knowledge. שלא בשבועה, Shelo Bishvuah, כרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, K'rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, like Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
that says that if there are witnesses that the father said on
the deathbed, he doesn't have to take an oath. But the פשט
pshat is that you see that you're taking the- that in the
scenario where the לוה lova died first and the מלוה malveh would
take an oath, and then the מלוה malveh dies, the children collect
with their oath even though it's not their father's oath against Rav
and Shmuel. So that seems like a pretty darn good proof against
Rav and Shmuel. So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, הא מני
בית שמאי היא, Ha Mani Beis Shamai He, דאמרי שטר העומד לגבות
כגבוי דמי. D'amri Shtar Ha'omed Ligvos K'gavuy Dami. So that's like another-
that's like another way of getting out of what seems to be
a clear proof. This is Beis Shamai. Beis Shamai says that once
you have a שטר shtar that should be collected, it's like the
money's already in the pocket. So when did we say that since
the kids can't take the same oath of the father, they lose
out? Remember the phrase was אין אדם מוריש שבועה לבניו, Ein Adam
Morish Shvuah Livnav, which I sort of said was like the money
is too of way- is too distant from you. It's only accessible
by an oath and you can't take the same oath. Well, he
says, Rav Nachman, according to Beis Shamai, because there's a שטר, shtar,
it's like the money was already in their father's pocket. Yes, it's
true, the father was obligated in an oath. But if you said
who is in possession of the money, so as opposed to before
we would say the לוה lova is in possession and you only
have access to it with the secret key, and the secret key
is the oath, and the kids can't take the oath, here we're
going to say, no, it's like the מלוה malveh is in possession
of the money. הלכתא, Halachsa, technically, he can't- you know, you know,
whatever, he won't- you know, we need him to make an oath.
But conceptually, the money's already in his pocket. Oh, if conceptually the
money's already in his pocket and then even if the kids can't
take exactly the same oath, they also can take the money. Okay,
so it's not like you have to bequeath this money, it's like
the money's already in his possession. All right, so that's how we
get out of it.
So bottom line is we got all this evidence against Rav and
Shmuel, but we haven't come to a conclusion. So now we're going
to tell a story. איקלע רב נחמן לסורא. Ikla Rav Nachman L'Sura.
So Rav Nachman
happened to visit Sura. עול לגבי רב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא.
Oul Ligabei Rav Chisda V'Rabbah Bar Rav Huna. Rav Chisda and Rabbah
Bar Rav Huna happened to drop by him. אמרו ליה, Amru Lei,
they said to him, ליסמי מר אקרוי דהלכותא דרב ושמואל. Lismai Mar
Akrei D'hilchosa D'Rav V'Shmuel.
You know, you Rav Nachman, you have so much- you know, you
have all of this power, you should come and you should like
just decree that we are getting rid of Rav and Shmuel's פסק.
psak. Okay, now that's pretty interesting, נעקרי, Na'akrei, like it had taken
some degree of root, you have to uproot it. But presumably for
the reason that Michael said, is that you can't run an- official,
a good society if, right, you have all these debts and based
on the order in which people died, it'll be impossible to collect.
Okay. אמר להו, Amar Lehu, so he said to them, איכבי ואתי
כל הני פרסאי למעקרא להדא דרב ושמואל? Ichbi V'Asi Kol Hanei Parsai
L'ma'akra L'hada D'Rav V'Shmuel? You're telling me that I traveled all of
these hundreds of miles so that I should come here and you
should want me to go against Rav and Shmuel? Okay. So they
said, ah, yeah, that's exactly what we're hoping. But no, אלא אהוסיפו
לא תוסיפו עלה. Ela Ahosifu Lo Sosifu Alah. I'll-
I'll make you the following concession: don't add to it. You know,
they have their weight of their authority behind it. Now, you could
generalize this to other cases where there's an obligation of a שבועה
shvuah and that, you know, you can't pass it on. No, we're
going- we're not going to go against their authority, but we're not
going to add to it. Even very similar cases, we're going to
say those cases the heirs will be allowed to take a שבועה.
shvuah. Only the case they ruled about, the heirs won't be able
to take a שבועה. shvuah. So now we're going to look at
what's considered to be a similar case where- or you know, to
be like a case that would be included in their ruling and
a case that would not. אהוסיפו לא תוסיפו עלה. Ahosifu Lo Sosifu
Alah. Just don't add to it. כגון מאי? Kegon Mai? What would
be an example? דאמר רב פפא הפוגם את שטרו ומת. D'amar Rav
Pappa Hapogem Es Shtaro U'meys. Let's say it's not a question about-
about heirs. Let's say it's a case about-
so
you know, somebody's coming to collect, Reuven is coming to collect from
Shimon, and he admits that part of the debt has been paid.
But he has- he has a שטר. shtar. But Reuven admits that
part of the debt has been paid. It's like a מודה במקצת
modeh b'miktzas but it's the reverse. So the הלכה halacha is Reuven
can only collect the balance of the שטר shtar if he takes
an oath. And then Reuven dies. So Reuven's kids can't take an
oath for sure. They can just take an oath to the best
of our knowledge, right? You get it? So it's not the oath
that you make to the heirs of the לוה, lova, it's an
oath made to the לוה lova himself. And then Reuven dies. Okay.
So הפוגם את שטרו ומת יורשין נשבעין שבועת יורשין ונוטלין. Hapogem Es
Shtaro U'meys Yorshin Nishba'in Shvuas Yorshin V'notlin. So then we would not
apply Rav and Shmuel. One would say, oh, well, the heirs can't
make the same oath their father- no. We're only going to say
Rav and Shmuel by the heir. An oath of the heirs to
the heirs. For another oath, a person who was obligated died, his
heirs can take their variation of it, to the best of our
knowledge version of it, and still collect.
Okay, what's the difference?
There is no difference. The difference is it wasn't a case that
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel ruled on. So we don't really like
רב Rav and שמואל's Shmuel ruling, but we're not prepared to reject
it, but we're going to just say we're going to just פסקן
pasken it in the one case that they פסקן. paskened.
I mean, I sort of see that, but then...
Okay, let's keep on going.
Okay. But didn't רב נחמן Rav Nachman himself say, had we ruled
like him, we wouldn't?
Right. So that's why you're correct, which is why they were hoping
that רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, who was not certain we ruled like
him, would basically be prepared to reject them, but he says, "No,
I'm not prepared to go that far." Okay, so it's a way
of splitting your vote. It's a bizarre way because there doesn't seem
to be a conceptual distinction. You will see in a minute how
much the גמרא Gemara wants to limit רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel,
that it really suggests cases where there's no distinction to be made,
and then it's going to sort of say, "Whatever, let's take a
look." Okay.
ההוא דשכיב ושביק ערבא. hahu deshachiv veshavik arva. Somebody died and there
was left over
a cosigner to collect from. Okay, so this was a case that
he would have had to take an oath to the cosigner and
then he died, and then his kids now, do they take an
oath to the cosigner? Similar to the oath of heirs to heirs,
but it's an oath of heirs to the cosigner. סבר רב פפא
למימר הני נמי דלאו
ספי להו. savar Rav Papa lemeimar hani nami d'lo sefi lehu. "Oh,
we should... this is a little bit different than רב Rav and
שמואל's Shmuel original ruling, so..." the heirs can take an oath. It's
not the case of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. They were talking
about heirs to heirs; this is heirs to cosigner. אמר ליה רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב פפא אטו ערבא לאו בתר יתמי אזל?
amar lei Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua leRav Papa atu arva lav
basar yasmi azil? No, because in this case, right, apparently there was
both heirs and the cosigner, okay? So here this guy who died,
he left heirs, but there was a cosigner that you would go
to first, he was the ערב. arev. So this was heirs to
cosigner; they were going to collect from the cosigner, okay? So he
said, "Ah, that's not exactly רב Rav and שמואל; Shmuel; it's heirs
to cosigner, not heirs to heirs." But he says, "Wait, if they
win and collect from the cosigner, the cosigner's going to go to
get reimbursed from the heirs." So effectively it's heirs to heirs, and
therefore you can't say it's not the same as the רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel case.
So he said a second ago it's not the same,
because there it wasn't actual this; there was a case of פוגם.
pogem. It was an oath being taken to the לווה loveh himself.
This is an oath that effectively is heirs to heirs; the other
case was heirs to the לווה. loveh.
If you really want to limit the scope of רב Rav and
שמואל... Shmuel...
I understand. So that's the question exactly how, you know, how much
you can split the hair. Okay. ההוא דשכיב ושביק אחא. hahu deshachiv
veshavik acha.
Now, somebody died, the מלווה malveh died, and he didn't leave sons,
he left a brother. So now it's a brother swearing to the
heirs of the לווה. loveh. Not sons to sons, but brother to
sons, okay? סבר רמי בר חמא למימר הני נמי דלאו ספי להו.
savar Rami bar Chama lemeimar hani nami d'lo sefi lehu. Okay,
good, let's not apply the רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel הלכה. halacha.
That's a little different, that's a brother, that's not sons. אמר ליה
רבא מה לי שלא פקדתני אבא מה לי שלא פקדתני אחי? amar
lei Rava mah li shelo pkadsani abba mah li shelo pkadsani achi?
Give me a break, it's heirs to heirs, who cares if the
oath is "My father didn't tell me otherwise" or "My brother didn't
tell me otherwise"? So I get that you want to limit רב
Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, but you can't make completely arbitrary distinctions. אמר
רב חמא. amar Rav Chama. So now let's just wrap this up.
השתא דלא איתמר הלכתא לא כרב ושמואל ולא כרבי אלעזר. hashta d'lo
itmar hilchasa lo keRav uShmuel velo keRabbi Eliezer. Now that the ruling
wasn't like רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel says that they're stuck in
that case when the לווה loveh died first, and not like רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that no, they can make their שבועת
היורשין. shvuas hayorshin. So האי דעבד כרב ושמואל עבד דעבד כרבי אלעזר
עבד. hai de'avad keRav uShmuel avad de'avad keRabbi Eliezer avad. Any judge
has the option of ruling whichever way they feel is the most
correct in this... So, by the way, that's... anyway,
that's better than the previous ruling. The previous ruling made it sound
like we're locked
into רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, but we limit the cases where
we're locked in. This is actually more freeing. This is saying you're
not locked in at all. It's the choice of the judges to
decide who to rule like. Okay, you really have to decide which
court you're going to פסקן pasken your case in. אמר רב פפא
האי שטרא דיתמי. amar Rav Papa hai shtra deyasmi. Now, if you
have this case of a שטר shtar from a case that, you
know, the father died first and had to make an oath... I'm
sorry, the לווה loveh died first, and the father had to make
an oath, and then the מלווה malveh died. So you have this
שטר shtar and we don't know how to, right, you know, you
can rule either like רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel or against them.
So לא מקרע קרעינן ליה ולא אגבויי מגבינן ביה. lo mikra karinan
lei velo agvoyi magbinan bei. We don't tear it up, and we
don't collect it. אגבויי לא מגבינן ביה. agvoyi lo magbinan bei. We
don't say we definitely are going to just collect, use it to
collect. Why? דלמא סבירא לן כרב ושמואל. dilma sevira lan keRav uShmuel.
Maybe we hold like רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, and since they
can't make the same oath as their father, they're out. ומקרע לא
קרעינן ליה, umikra lo karinan lei, and we don't tear it
up, דהאי דיינא דעבד כרבי אלעזר עבד, dehai dayna de'avad keRabbi Eliezer
avad, because maybe there'll be a judge that wants to rule like
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, basically, so... but it's like, yeah, that's
a good question. It's also a little bit bizarre. What does it
mean we don't tear it up and we don't collect? He just
says it's a ספק. safek. What we do with it is going
to depend on which judge you go to. It's like, that's like
a strange point, but I mean maybe it's sort of like... I
don't know. Maybe it's saying if you're I have no idea. Okay,
anyway. ההוא דיינא דעבד כרבי אליעזר. Hahu dayna de-avad ke-Rabbi Eliezer. So
there was a judge who ruled like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. ההוא
צורבא מרבנן דמטא, Hahu tzurba me-rabanan de-mta, ההוא צורבא מרבנן דמטא. Hahu
tzurba me-rabanan de-mta. So there was a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham in
the city. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אייתינא איגרתא ממערבא, ayseina igrasa mi-ma'arava,
I'm going to get a letter from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael דלא
כרבי אליעזר, delo ke-Rabbi Eliezer, we don't rule like him, which is
pretty funny, because until now רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel have been
the בבל Bavel approach, and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael seems to have
been the approach, you know, more inclined to basically say that you
can collect. And he says, I'm going to get a proof from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that even ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they agree
that you're not allowed to collect in this case. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, לכי תייתי שקייך, lechi teisi shkayach, when you go get
the letter come back to me, okay? Don't
until then stop bothering me. Okay, אתא לקמיה דרב חמא, Ata lekamei
de-Rav Chama, he came to רב חמא Rav Chama and he said,
can you give me a letter to say that you're not allowed
to rule like this? It's going against רב Rav and שמואל? Shmuel?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, האי דיינא דעבד כרבי אליעזר עבד. hai dayna
de-avad ke-Rabbi Eliezer avad. No, he was in his right. If you
want to rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you can. It sounds
like by the end that there is a little bit of a
default like רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, at least so it sounds
like right, and therefore like if you פוסק posken like רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer it's also okay. It still sounds like the default. So
in the end, it sort of sounds like רב Rav and שמואל's
Shmuel position carried weight and became a default, but number one, we
wanted to limit it to only the case of ארוס arus from
ארוסה, arusa, not other types of cases. And number two, even in
that type of a case, a דיין dayan would have the discretion
to choose to rule like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and to rule
against רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, we'll end with this.